Three years ago, my family and I moved to Cornwall to live the green life, and we ended up here at Newhouse Farm, where we built a water wheel to make electricity to light the house, become virtually self-sufficient in fruit and veg, but, unfortunately, not yet in wine.
And I traded my gorgeous little sports car for a much more sensible agricultural vehicle that runs on biodiesel made from chip fat.
We're back with a magazine programme, which means we've got something for everybody.
Each week, rock chick and TV presenter Lauren Laverne will be investigating the posh end of the green market.
I just hope they're not skimping on the luxury.
And we'll be paying regular visits to the green end of the housing market.
Hi, Dick, Jane and Chris here.
We've got this Victorian house that we'd like to to eco renovate.
And there'll be interviews with famous people, like Phil Tufnell.
How are you getting home?
Um, plane!
It's a long way!
You live miles away!
And still time to show you what we're getting up to at Newhouse Farm.
With plenty of top tips for a tiptop eco lifestyle.
Here's a thought for you - it's not easy being green.
Never has been, probably never will be, but it's an awful lot of fun trying.
I know you lot are probably sitting shivering at home in front of the fire, but it's summertime here.
That means you have to put up with my shorts and rather hairy legs while we crack on with our latest project - our very sexy PV panels.
Photovoltaic panels use sunlight to make electricity, and these little beauties are going to make us self sufficient in power.
Master James Strawbridge has become quite the expert.
This is a hybrid mono crystalline system, it's got 20% efficiency, and somehow, scientifically, the sun hits them and they make electricity.
I think it's a bit of magic.
James did a history degree, but, look, it's that easy!
So light comes in here, it makes electricity, and what do we do with it?
Send it in the house and hopefully we'll get a year's supply from it.
Interested?
Then you'll need a south facing roof or wall strong enough to support the panels.
Very soon, no fossil fuels will be burned to make my cups of tea, which just as well seeing as I have so much entertaining to do over the series.
Each week, I'll be inviting a guest to take our eco test.
Victim number one is...
Phil!
I've come prepared.
Got my boots on.
Do you know why you're here?
Well, not really.
Good man, come on.
'Phil Tufnell, but first up, a tour of the estate.'
I'm a little bit green.
Obviously, what we've done here is try to set up as much as we possibly can.
We're making our own electricity.
You're not into that sort of thing, are you?
Make you're own electricity, like a scientist!
Yeah!
Not quite.
There you go, so what's up here?
You don't look as if you eat enough.
No, well, I was a sportsman, you know?
We grow quite a lot of our own stuff.
Yes, yes.
Now, I know a couple of mates who grow their own stuff now, and they're kind of...
It's quite funny, isn't it?
These boys were cool kind of guys around town and now they all go down the allotment and start growing tomatoes, which is quite weird!
Have a bite of that.
I know you like tomatoes.
Does it need to be washed?
No, it doesn't!
There's nothing on it nasty.
That is a good tom, that is.
It's not bad, is it?
No, no, it's a good tom.
With all these things growing we're making our wine and doing our stuff.
Do you know why?
Because we can.
We've got these little bad boys.
What are they?
These are ducks, and geese in this bit here.
We've got these in here because we eat the ducks, and we...
A l'orange.
And we eat their eggs, duck eggs, yes.
What's up with the faces?
Warts.
That's the way they're meant to be.
That's what they look like.
They're just the world's ugliest ducks.
They're ugly ducklings, aren't they?
They're genetically done like that so you don't feel bad about eating them!
This is something dear to your heart, I suppose.
Because you know about making biodiesel?
Is it like the chip shop?
Yes.
Old chip oil that we turn into our diesel.
How much are you paying for a litre?
I don't know!
£25 or something.
How much is a litre?
I don't know.
This is a worry if you don't even know how much it costs.
You fill your tank up and it's a hundred quid.
We make this for 14p a litre, which is quite...
Could I do this?
Could I go down my local?
Anybody can do this.
It looks quite complicated.
Nah.
We built that.
The toilet.
Yeah.
It's a compost loo.
Very nice.
Curtain in there.
Will you come in?
The trepidation!
But, actually, it's a nice place to be.
It's all right.
When you're working in the garden, pull that up and it goes in...
There's a big cavity where you do it, and then you put some sawdust in it afterwards and at the end of it, we make compost.
All the poop turns into compost.
And you stick it on the veg.
I've just eaten that tomato, haven't I!
Have I just been eating your...
Didn't I tell you that?!
You ain't got one of these then?
No, I haven't got one of these.
I don't know whether the missus would be too happy with it, but I'll have to put it to her.
So we've got to the bottom of my green lifestyle.
Later in the show, I'll be asking Phil some difficult questions about his.
But I can't spend all day hanging out with luvvies.
I've got man work to do on my PV panels.
That part of the roof is perfect for capturing sunshine because it points due south.
But that's the easy bit.
Now we have to take a cable from the control panel in the course barn, under this concrete, get all the way round to the back of the house, about 60 metres, and then we connect it to the National Grid.
But we don't want to dig up the concrete, because replacing it is one of the most environmentally unfriendly things you can do.
It's probably like an eighth of all the carbon footprint in the world comes from making concrete.
So we're using a mechanical mole to burrow under the yard.
The trouble, is I'm not sure where the wretched thing is.
What they're doing, if we're completely honest, we're trying to find it.
Here it comes!
All right, lads!
That's moving quickly, isn't it?
You did that, sort of five metres across there in, what, less than ten minutes.
The mechanical mole team are all ready laying the cable.
And we're making headway through the soft ground.
A few hours later, job done.
In fact, you want to know something, let's get a beer.
A hard day's work.
Luckily, we've got a top tip for sweaty chaps.
James Strawbridge presents: an eco alternative to chemical deodorants.
Do you want to avoid getting unnecessary chemicals into your skin but still smell good?
Try Bauxite Crystal.
High performance eco control against body odour.
This crystal deposits salt on your skin, raising PH level, stopping bacteria in its tracks, as nature intended.
If you want to score, Rock Fresh gets results!
Yeah!
Rock, Rock, Rock Fresh!
Joking apart, you really can buy these things at any hippy dippy store or website.
Go on, try one!
But first, here's Lauren Laverne to tackle one of life's great dilemmas well, for some.
You know those things that just don't come in the sentence as environmentally friendly or sustainable?
Things that don't even come in the colour green?
But you really, really want one.
Looking for an eco friendly swimming pool is like trying to find an eco friendly nuclear bomb.
It's just not possible.
But there are ways to make these works of the devil little bit less devil like.
It is possible to spend your way out of environmental embarrassment.
What we've got in the background going on is a drilling rig drilling 100-metre deep holes for the geothermal heat pump that will provide all the energy to heat the house, heat the hot water and heat the swimming pool and swimming pool air.
There's a pipe in and out, what we call a closed loop.
We're taking the heat out of the earth and that's what being used to run the heat pump.
This is expensive to put in, but on a house of this size where we have a big house with a swimming pool, you're looking at a repayment over three or four years.
They're doing their best, but they could do better.
Or you could have one like this, where nature does all the heating and bacteria eating for you, and there isn't even a muddy bottom.
So Will, what actually is this?
Is it a swimming pool, a pond, or something in between the two?
It's something in between the two.
It's a natural swimming pool.
This is the ultimate in enviro chic no chemicals to buy, and the little pump that swishes the water round only uses a quarter of the power needed for a regular pool.
A natural swimming pool pump only has to run while the plants are actually actively growing during the daytime.
So you've automatically halved the amount of time.
Six to eight hours is enough.
This is the carbonator which helps feed the plants, and it also means if the plants are healthy, they're giving oxygen to all the organisms that actually clean the water.
They're not just organisms they is bugs!
OK, Hal, so I understand you know a lot about the wildlife around this pool pond?
Just found a water snail.
Yes, look at that!
What about the snail poo, is that not a problem?
That's not really a problem.
Feel like I'm shadowing a young David Bellamy here.
There's a water boatman there.
OK.
They just skate on the water.
And be assured, viewer, no bugs were harmed in the making of this film.
It's an animal friendly skimmer.
Any animals or bugs that get caught in it can either swim back at night or climb out the back safely, and get back into the pond overland.
I think I'd be quite squeamish about bugs and insects.
Are there are a lot of those little critters in there if I was going to swim in there?
Most of the larger species keep to the edges, in the plants where the main habitat is, but there is smaller microscopic bugs through the swimming area.
These actually clean the water, so they're an important part of it.
So how clean?
Can you show us?
This water we tested recently, two months ago, and it was drinking water quality, so it's fine to drink.
Really?
Can you...?
In fact, the water tastes quite sweet.
It's...
Delicious.
Would you like some?
OK, go on, then.
That is actually really nice!
It's lovely, yeah.
A top of the range pool like this will set you back over £100,000.
All swimming pools are expensive, but at least these don't cost the earth, and you can invite your friends over and watch them go green with envy.
OK...
Dry clean only, but... fine.
It's a bit like the Lost Boys in here.
Up next: Our first visit of many to Chris Mead and Jaye Hayter.
Hi, Dick, we've got this Victorian house that we'd like to eco renovate.
We're looking at wall insulation, loft insulation, green ideas for solar energy, alternative energy, wind power, wind turbine.
Any of your magnificent inventions can come along that would fit snugly into a Victorian house.
That's what we'd be interested in.
'Flattery will get you everywhere.'
Let's go into the lounge.
This is the lounge.
This is our front room of our...
So, this is the lounge!
It will be!
Where's the sofa?
Look at the floorboards.
Are you going to keep them?
Yes, we will sand them down, keep them as original, but they're very good solid floors.
Chris and Jaye have £100,000 of their hard earned cash to green up this wreck of a house in London.
They want it to be an all singing, all dancing temple to green technology.
There's a huge amount to be done.
We're talking blank canvasses.
Can you do almost anything.
'There's damp in the basement.'
Used to have air bricks, but over a period of time, they've all been blocked up, and it's starting to smell.
The whole house needs rewiring and replumbing, and so does the garden.
I want chickens out there!
I want free range eggs.
'And this will be the control centre for all the green technology.'
Hopefully, this is going to be an eco comms room.
Not yet!
Their hundred grand has to go a long way to create a bijou residence, complete with solar power and state of the art heating.
Thinking about your priorities, if you've got the idea you want solar PV and under floor heating, but perhaps if we look around, insulation might be the first thing you need to focus on.
It's very easy to think, "let's go green, let's buy solar panels".
James is absolutely right.
Lot of insulation is the best way to start, and could cut heating bills by £200 a year or more.
And this is my favourite kind.
Sheep's wool.
This isn't cheap.
Any insulation is good insulation, and this is green, so it's good.
Sheep's wool costs four times as much as the cheapest insulation on the market.
But Jaye thinks she's worth it.
This is brilliant.
You can put it up, you're not given any fibres, manmade fibres on your hands, you can take it down, it's malleable.
It's brilliant.
It's naturally fire retardant.
It's got to be laid properly into the edges.
That's where James comes in.
It's important to get it into the eaves, because all those awkward little corners that I can get in that my dad can't... !
It's really important, because if you've got one gap, then it's almost like all this is worthless.
Our houses are responsible for a quarter of the carbon emissions in the UK.
Half of the heat loss in a typical home is through the roof and loft.
We're having to put three layers of insulation up because you need about 270mm, a foot in old money, of insulation in your roof.
No good saying you've got insulation with four inches of fibre glass The more you put up, the more heat you keep in, which means the less energy you use every winter when you're heating your house.
So, this is a good investment, and you only ever do it once because get enough in there, and you'll stay warm.
Over the next six months, this place is going to be a hive of activity.
From the top of the roof to the bottom of the garden.
And don't forget, they want chickens!
It does.
We'll be with them every step of the way.
OK, eurgh!
Done!
Yeah!
Nice and warm, it feels good.
They've got a long way to go.
I hope they know what they've let themselves in for, because we've been here for three years, and we keep finding new things to do.
And most of them are aimed at trying to save us money.
Our PV panels are no exception.
Jim!
How much electricity today?
Look how much!
Only Jim's going to have something like that in his pocket.
300 watts per square metre today.
We don't want days like this, we want sunshine, we want it to pay for itself, have a bit of an income.
'Because this job ain't cheap.'
It's all right, one person's allowed to do that to me!
How much does it cost, mate?
This particular system is going to cost about £15,000, which is a bargain!
He said that with a straight face!
We're paying £15,000 for our insulation, where we get £2,500 grant, so, for £12,500, we're probably getting enough photovoltaics to keep us in electricity for a very long time.
Ooh, the last one!
If we were to connect this to that wire, we'd be making electricity.
We would, but we'd give Jim a bit of a shock.
Because he's connecting the wire.
All right, which one do we put it in?!
Bearing in mind you could easily spend about £1,000 a year on electricity for a house like ours, the panels will pay for themselves eventually.
What are you doing?
Waiting for the sun!
With every bit of kit we install here at Newhouse Farm, our carbon footprint is getting smaller and smaller, but how do we compare with other people?
There's one way to find out.
Each week, we'll be whipping out our ecological calculator to put a guest to the eco test.
Of all the calculators on the Web, we've picked this one by the WWF.
It's fairly quick to do, that's telly for you, and gives a clear and simple picture of your impact on the world.
By answering a series of questions, we'll get a measure of how many planets would be needed to support life if everyone in the world lived the same way as them.
I was a bit peeved by my score of 2.4 planets, but this calculator isn't designed for somebody who's all ready doing lots of green projects, it's designed for normal people like Phil Tufnell.
I've got some simple questions, and this gives a flavour for how you use the energy and resources in your life.
Righto.
How would you describe your diet?
All round, love everything.
Meat?
Yes.
You're not a vegetarian, are you, mate?
No, I'm not.
Fish, everything, veggies, lovely.
Right.
In the last 12 months, have you bought any of the following: television or a hi-fi?
Yes.
The answer is supposed to be no, to be brief!
Oh, is it?
I was feeling all proud!
I bought a great big telly!
You said yes and you were so pleased with yourself!
Good man, OK.
There we go.
I quite like this question: What kind of vehicle do you travel in?
This is where I fall down, and I will drive up to the paper shop to get me paper instead of having a walk or getting on a bike.
I'd say naughty boy on that one.
Which of these best describes the vehicle you use most?
Oh dear.
Sodding large!
Yeah.
It's 4.4.
You've got to have a bit of fun being green as well.
You've got to have a bit of a laugh, haven't you?
There's nothing green about having a 4.4 litre petrol car.
I feel very ashamed and I'm going to get rid of it.
I still need a big car and a 4x4 because I live out in the country a little bit, but, as you say, 4.4.
You say a little bit, you say you live out the country and then you add a little bit?
Well, no, a little bit.
So you need a 4x4.
You've got lanes and little tracks as well that you have to go down, so you can't be doing it in a Mini, mate!
It's not working on me!
I'm not feeling the mud!
All right, OK, I'll sell it tomorrow!
How do you heat your home?
Erm...
Gas central heating.
Gas?
Yes.
Boiler, radiators.
Do you buy your electricity on a green tariff?
Erm...
You don't even know what you pay for your electricity!
What is a green tariff?
You can buy green electricity, pay the same price as you pay for ordinary electricity.
And they don't have to put a great big hose...
They don't do anything.
It's just green electricity?
You just buy renewable.
How warm do you keep your home?
Cool, comfortable, warm or hot?
I would say comfortable.
Which is 14 to 17 degrees.
That's...
Oh, yes...
I thought it would have been about 19.
No, 19 is warm.
Is it?
OK.
Yeah.
I don't have the heating on in the summer.
Really, Phil?
You don't just think that's common sense?
No, but I'd keep it normal, comfortable.
Comfortable for you.
Your footprint, to support you, if everybody in the UK lived like you, we'd actually need 3.97 planets.
Is that really bad?
It's quite a lot of planets, mate.
Yeah.
It means that you're sort of that's a lot of planets being used up.
How are you getting home?
Erm...
Plane.
It's a long way!
You live miles away!
A plane?!
Hold on!
I in live England.
It may be Cornwall and, yes, but don't hide!
I'm getting a plane.
But it runs on chip fat!
It's a long way back to Surrey on a horse and cart.
It will make me about three weeks.
Mr Tufnell, you're the first guest to take the eco test.
It makes me feel a bit better about my score.
It's not easy being green!
It's not that difficult!
On a good day, we should be making more electricity than we need, but here's the thing: we can sell that power back to the National Grid.
Ready, Andy?
We're ready.
And even better, next year, the Government are going to double the price paid for surplus power, which will reduce my payback by about five years.
If you want to know more, check out the website at: Come on!
This great gadget tells me how much electricity is being made right now.
It's not the sun, it's the machine.
It takes three minutes to warm up.
So take a look at what's coming up next week.
Lauren gets to grips with furniture recycling.
We could buy that plain Victorian beach chair.
How much do you think?
£100.
£3.
No!
£3?!
And in London, James persuades Bridget to join her for a spot of gardening.
Look at the snails!
Kill 'em.
No!
And we examine the plight of the honeybee with rock star Alex James.
Well, Martin, to be or not to be, that is the question!
What's the answer?
Look at that.
'Now, buzz off!'
Yes!
2,331!
That gorgeous number, in fact, enough to power the house right now, which means...
That's enough for tea!
Get the kettle on!